Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 55: Thromboembolic Disorders.
Pathophysiology Thrombophilias Antiphospholipid Syndrome Thrombophilia Screening Deep-Vein Thrombosis Labor And Delivery Superficial Venous Thrombophlebitis Pulmonary Embolism Thromboprophylaxis References During the past century, the frequency of venous thromboembolism (VTE) during the puerperium decreased remarkably as early ambulation became routine practice.
Despite this and other advances in prevention and treatment, thromboembolism remains a leading cause of maternal morbidity and mortality .
Thrombotic pulmonary embolism accounted for almost 10 percent of pregnancy-related deaths in the United States between 2011 and 2015 (Creanga, 2017; Petersen, 2019).
The absolute incidence of VTE during pregnancy is low—1 or 2 cases per 1000 pregnancies.
However, the risk is approximately five times higher than that among women who are not pregnant .
Approximately equal numbers of cases are identified antepartum and in the puerperium.
But deep-vein thrombosis alone is more frequent antepartum, and pulmonary embolism is more common postpartum.
During the first 6 weeks of the puerperium, the estimated incidence of a thromboembolic complication is 22 events per 100,000 deliveries.
Although still elevated, the risk falls to approximately 3 cases per 100,000 deliveries during the second 6-week postpartum period .
As many as 2 percent of these women have postthrombotic syndrome .
Pathophysiology.
Rudolf Virchow (1856) postulated that stasis, local trauma to the vessel wall, and hypercoagulability predisposed to venous thrombosis.
During pregnancy, the risk for each of these rises.
Compression of the pelvic veins and inferior vena cava by the enlarging uterus renders the lower extremity venous system particularly vulnerable to stasis.
Marik and Plante (2008) cite a 50-percent reduction in venous flow velocity in the legs that lasts from the early third trimester until 6 weeks postpartum.
This stasis is the most constant predisposing risk factor for venous thrombosis.
Venous stasis, delivery, preeclampsia, and sepsis contribute to endothelial cell injury.
Last, as listed in the Appendix (p. 1228), the synthesis of most clotting factors is markedly enhanced during pregnancy and favors coagulation.
Risk factors for developing VTE during pregnancy are shown in Table 55-1.
The most important of these is a personal history of thrombosis.
Specifically, 15 to 25 percent of all VTE cases during pregnancy are recurrent events .
Another important individual risk factor is a genetically determined thrombophilia.
An estimated 20 to 50 percent of women who develop a venous thrombosis during pregnancy or postpartum have an identifiable underlying procoagulant genetic disorder .
Table 55-1.
Some Risk Factors Associated with an Increased Risk for VTE Calculated risks for thromboembolism are approximately doubled in women with multifetal gestation, anemia, hyperemesis, hemorrhage, cesarean delivery, obesity, preeclampsia, and postpartum infection .
Scheres and coworkers (2020) had similar observations for women with preeclampsia.
Risks were significantly higher among women who had a stillbirth or who underwent peripartum hysterectomy.
Last, as discussed in Chapter 57 (p. 1021), inflammatory bowel disease increases the risk two- to threefold .
Thrombophilias.
Several important regulatory proteins act as inhibitors in the coagulation cascade .
Normal values for many of these proteins during pregnancy are found in the Appendix (p. 1228).
Inherited or acquired deficiencies of these inhibitory proteins are collectively referred to as thrombophilias.
These can lead to hypercoagulability and recurrent VTE .
Although these disorders are collectively present in approximately 15 percent of white European populations, they are responsible for approximately 50 percent of all thromboembolic events during pregnancy .
Some aspects of the more common inherited thrombophilias related to VTE are summarized in Table 55-2.
Figure 55-1.
Inherited thrombophilias and their effect(s) on the coagulation cascade.
Table 55-2.
Inherited Thrombophilias and Their Association with Venous Thromboembolism (VTE) in Pregnancy # Inherited Thrombophilias.
Patients with inherited thrombophilic disorders often have a family history of thrombosis.
These mutations are also found in up to half of all patients who present with VTE before the age of 45 years, particularly in those whose event occurred in the absence of well-recognized risk factors.
Of greatest significance is a family history of sudden death due to pulmonary embolism or a history of multiple family members requiring long-term anticoagulation therapy because of recurrent thrombosis .
Antithrombin Deficiency Synthesized in the liver, antithrombin is one of the most important inhibitors of thrombin and inactivates thrombin and factor Xa (Rhéaume, 2016).
Notably, the rate of antithrombin interaction with its target is accelerated over 1000–fo1d by heparin.
Antithrombin deficiency may result from hundreds of different mutations that are almost always autosomal dominant.
Type I deficiency results from reduced synthesis of biologically normal antithrombin, and type II deficiency is characterized by normal levels of antithrombin with reduced functional activity.
Homozygous antithrombin deficiency is lethal.
Heterozygous deficiency affects approximately 1 in 2500 individuals.
It is the most thrombogenic of the heritable coagulopathies.
The risk for thrombosis correlates with the degree of deficiency.
Antithrombin deficiency is associated with a 25- to 50fold higher relative risk of VTE in the general population and a sixfold increased risk of thromboembolic complications during pregnancy .
As shown in Table 55-2, those affected have an inordinately high risk of VTE during pregnancy.
Sabadell and associates (2010) studied the outcomes of 18 pregnancies complicated by antithrombin deficiency.
Twelve of these women were treated with therapeutic doses of low-molecular-weight heparin (LMWH).
Three of the untreated patients suffered a thromboembolic episode compared with none in the treated group.
Untreated women also had a 50-percent risk of stillbirth and fetal-growth restriction.
By comparison, none of the treated women had a stillbirth, but a fourth developed fetal-growth restriction.
Abbattista and coworkers (2020) reported a 7-percent risk of VTE for women treated with LMWH during pregnancy and a 12-percent risk for those not treated.
Similar results were reported by Ilonczai and colleagues (2015).
Last, Garcia-Botella and associates (2016) described a mesenteric vein thrombosis in a pregnant woman with antithrombin deficiency.
Given such risk, affected women are managed during pregnancy with anticoagulation regardless of whether they have had a prior thrombosis (Abbattista, 2020; Bates, 2018).
When anticoagulation is necessarily withheld, such as during surgery or delivery, or if VTE develops in an anticoagulated woman, treatment with recombinant human antithrombin may be protective .
Protein C Deficiency When thrombin is bound to thrombomodulin on endothelial cells of small vessels, its procoagulant activities are neutralized.
This binding also activates protein C, a natural anticoagulant.
It, in the presence of protein S, controls thrombin generation, in part, by inactivating factors Va and VIIIa (see Fig. 55-1).
Protein C activity increases modestly but significantly throughout the first half of pregnancy, and some have speculated that this augmentation may play a role in maintaining early pregnancy through both anticoagulant and inflammatory regulatory pathways .
More than 160 different autosomal dominant mutations for the protein C gene have been described .
The prevalence of heterozygous protein C deficiency is 2 to 3 per 1000, but many of these individuals do not have a thrombosis history because the phenotypic expression is highly variable.
These prevalence estimates correspond with functional activity threshold values of 50 to 60 percent, which are used by most laboratories.
As shown in Table 55-2, these are associated with a sixto twelvefold higher risk for VTE .
The rare
cases of homozygous protein C deficiency may cause fatal neonatal purpura fulminans.
Last, sepsis can result in purpura fulminans in the adult with heterozygous protein C deficiency .
Protein S Deficiency This circulating anticoagulant is activated by protein C, which enhances the capacity of protein S to inactivate factors Va and VIIIa (see Fig. 55-1).
Protein S deficiency may be caused by more than 130 different mutations, with an aggregate heterozygous prevalence of approximately 0.3 to 1.3 per 1000 individuals .
Protein S deficiency may be measured by antigenically determined free, functional, and total S levels.
All three decline substantively during normal gestation (Appendix, p. 1228).
Thus, the diagnosis in pregnant women—as well as in those taking certain oral contraceptives—is difficult.
If screening during pregnancy is necessary, threshold values for free protein S antigen levels in the second and third trimesters have been identified at <30 percent and <24 percent, respectively.
The risk of VTE in pregnancy is increased severalfold .
Among those with a positive family history, the VTE risk in pregnancy is 6 to 7 percent .
Conard and coworkers (1990) described thrombosis in five of 29 pregnant women with protein S deficiency.
They, as well as Burneo and colleagues (2002), reported maternal cerebral vein thrombosis.
Neonatal homozygous protein S deficiency is usually associated with purpura fulminans, the fatal clinical phenotype.
Factor V Leiden Mutation This is the most prevalent of the known thrombophilia syndromes and is characterized by resistance of plasma to the anticoagulant effects of activated protein C.
There are several mutations that create this resistance, but the most common is the factor V Leiden mutation.
This missense mutation results from a substitution of glutamine for arginine at position 506 in the factor V polypeptide.
As a result of this mutation, activated factor V is neutralized approximately tenfold more slowly by activated protein C (see Fig. 55-1).
This leads to enhanced thrombin generation.
Heterozygous inheritance of factor V Leiden is the most common heritable thrombophilia.
It is found in 3 to 15 percent of select European populations, 1.2 percent of African Americans, and 2.2 of Hispanic Americans, but is virtually absent in African blacks and Asians .
Women who are heterozygous for factor V Leiden account for approximately 40 percent of VTE cases during pregnancy.
However, the actual risk among pregnant women who are heterozygous and who do not have a personal history or a first-degree relative with a thrombotic episode before age 50 years is 5 to 12 events per 1000 births .
In contrast, this risk is at least 10 percent among pregnant women with a personal or family history.
Pregnant women who are homozygous without a personal or family history have a 1to 4-percent risk for VTE, whereas those with such a history have an approximately 17-percent risk .
Diagnosis during pregnancy is performed by DNA analysis for the mutant factor V gene.
Bioassay is not used because of the normal resistance that develops after early pregnancy from alterations in other coagulation protein concentrations.
Of note, activated protein C resistance can also be caused by antiphospholipid syndrome, which is described on page 979 and also detailed in Chapter 62 (p. 1114).
To assess the prognostic significance of maternal factor V Leiden mutation during pregnancy, Kjellberg and associates (2010) compared the outcomes of 491 carriers with those of 1055 controls.
All three of the thromboembolic events occurred among the carriers.
But, preterm birth rates, birthweights, or hypertensive complication rates did not differ between the two groups.
In a prospective observational study of almost 5000 women conducted by the Maternal-Fetal Medicine Units Network, the heterozygous mutant gene incidence was 2.7 percent .
Of three pulmonary emboli and one deep-vein thrombosis cases—a rate of 0.8 per 1000 pregnancies—none was among these carriers.
Moreover, in the heterozygous women, the risks of
preeclampsia, placental abruption, fetalgrowth restriction, or pregnancy loss were not elevated.
The investigators concluded that universal prenatal screening for the Leiden mutation and prophylaxis for carriers without a prior VTE is not indicated.
Prothrombin G20210A Mutation This missense mutation in the prothrombin gene leads to excessive accumulation of prothrombin, which may be converted to thrombin.
Prothrombin levels are increased approximately 30 percent in heterozygotes and 70 percent in homozygotes .
As with factor V Leiden, a personal or family history of VTE in a first-degree relative before age 50 years raises the risk of VTE during pregnancy .
For a heterozygous carrier with such a history, the risk exceeds 10 percent.
Without such a history, heterozygous carriers of the mutation have less than a 1percent risk of VTE during pregnancy .
Silver and coworkers (2010) tested nearly 4200 women for the prothrombin G20210A mutation.
A total of 157—or 3.8 percent—of the women carried the mutation, and only one of these was homozygous.
Carriers had similar rates of pregnancy loss, preeclampsia, fetal-growth restriction, and placental abruption compared with noncarriers.
Three thromboembolic events occurred in women who tested negative for the mutation.
Homozygous patients, or those who are doubly heterozygous for a G20210A mutation with a factor V Leiden mutation, have a greater thromboembolism risk than heterozygous carriers .
Others have provided detailed information on pregnancy outcomes in women with such rare compound thrombophilias (Carroll, 2018; Lim, 2016).
Hyperhomocysteinemia The most common cause of elevated homocysteine is the C667T thermolabile mutation of the 5, 10– methylene–tetrahydrofolate reductase (MTHFR) enzyme.
Inheritance is autosomal recessive.
Elevated homocysteine levels may also result from deficiency of one of several enzymes involved in methionine metabolism and from correctible nutritional deficiencies of folic acid, vitamin B6, or vitamin B12.
During normal pregnancy, mean homocysteine plasma concentrations decline and make a diagnosis difficult .
A metaanalysis by den Heijer and associates (2005) reported an association between MTHFR polymorphisms and a slightly greater risk for thrombosis in international studies, but no such association was found in North American studies (den Heijer, 2005).
The authors speculated that folic acid supplementation could explain the difference.
Recall that folic acid serves as a cofactor in the remethylation reaction of homocysteine to methionine.
Similarly, the American College of Chest Physicians posited that the lack of an association with thromboembolism could reflect the physiological reductions in homocysteine levels associated with pregnancy as well as the effects of widespread prenatal folic acid supplementation .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) has concluded that there is insufficient evidence to support assessment of MTHFR polymorphisms or measurement of fasting homocysteine levels in the evaluation for VTE.
Other Thrombophilia Mutations Protein Z is a vitamin K–dependent protein that serves as a cofactor in factor Xa inactivation.
Studies have found that low protein Z levels are associated with an elevated thromboembolism risk in nonpregnant patients and may be implicated in the pathogenesis of poor pregnancy outcomes .
Similarly, plasminogen activator inhibitor type 1 (PAI-I) is an important regulator of fibrinolysis.
Certain polymorphisms in the gene promoter have been associated with slightly higher VTE risks.
Although these thrombophilias may exacerbate risk among patients when coinherited with other thrombophilias, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) has concluded that evidence to recommend screening is insufficient.
# Acquired Thrombophilias.
Some examples of acquired hypercoagulable states include antiphospholipid syndrome (APS), heparin-induced thrombocytopenia, and cancer.
Antiphospholipid Syndrome This prothrombotic disorder can affect both the venous and
arterial circulations.
The deeper veins of the lower limbs and the cerebral arterial circulation are the most frequent sites of venous and arterial thrombosis, respectively (Garcia, 2018; Konkle, 2018).
Besides thrombosis, the other major clinical manifestations of APS are adverse obstetrical outcomes (Table 11-4, p. 205).
Criteria for APS include (1) at least one otherwise unexplained fetal death at or beyond 10 weeks; (2) at least one preterm birth before 34 weeks’ gestation because of eclampsia, severe preeclampsia, or placental insufficiency; or (3) at least three unexplained consecutive spontaneous abortions before 10 weeks.
The syndrome is discussed in detail in Chapter 62 (p. 1114).
Testing for antiphospholipid antibodies should be performed in women with an unexplained arterial or venous thromboembolism or a history of one fetal loss or three or more recurrent embryonic or fetal losses .
At this time, preterm severe preeclampsia and early-onset placental insufficiency do not support such testing.
That said, there is evidence that antiphospholipid positivity confers a worse prognosis for pregnancies complicated by HELLP syndrome (Pécourt, 2021).
These patients should be tested for the presence of three factors: (1) lupus anticoagulant, (2) anticardiolipin immunoglobulin G and M (IgG and IgM) antibodies, and (3) anti-β2 glycoprotein-I IgG and IgM antibodies.
If any of these laboratory test results are positive, a confirmatory test is performed 12 weeks later .
Based on their study of 750 singleton pregnancies complicated by APS, Saccone and colleagues (2017) found that anticardiolipin antibody is the most common sole antiphospholipid antibody present.
Women with APS have a 5- to 12-percent risk of thrombosis during pregnancy or the puerperium.
Indeed, up to 25 percent of these thrombotic events occur during pregnancy or in the puerperium.
# Thrombophilias and Pregnancy Complications.
Contrary to past teaching, no definite causal link between inherited thrombophilias and adverse pregnancy outcomes exists .
The confusion was caused by a number of observational studies that were later followed by large prospective cohort studies.
Currently, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) does not recommend inherited thrombophilia screening for women with a history of fetal loss or adverse pregnancy outcomes such as fetal-growth restriction, placental abruption, and preeclampsia.
There are no convincing data that link inherited thrombophilias and fetal loss.
It follows that there is no benefit to aspirin or heparin therapy as might accrue for recurrent pregnancy loss due to antiphospholipid antibodies .
Stillbirths also are not more common with heterozygous mutations, but there is a weak association with homozygous factor V Leiden mutation .
Last, there is insufficient evidence to screen for inherited thrombophilias in women with a fetal death .
Fetal-growth restriction also is not more common with inherited thrombophilias (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020a; Infante-Rivard, 2002).
Likewise, there have been a number of prospective cohort studies that showed no association of inherited thrombophilias with placental abruption (Dizon-Townson, 2005; Silver, 2010).
Conversely, Alfirevic and coworkers (2002) reported an association with these and both heterozygosity and homozygosity for factor V Leiden mutations as well as heterozygous prothrombin G20210A mutation.
Studies showing an association of inherited thrombophilias and preeclampsia also are conflicting .
One large systematic review and metaanalysis of nearly 22,000 women did not show an association between factor V Leiden or prothrombin gene mutations with preeclampsia .
Similarly, a more recent prospective study failed to show an association between preeclampsia and 12 hereditary thrombophilias .
Thus, because of uncertainties in the magnitude of risk and in the benefits of prophylaxis given to prevent pregnancy complications in women with heritable thrombophilias, it remains unproven that universal screening is
indicated .
In contrast, the association between APS and adverse pregnancy outcomes—including fetal loss, recurrent pregnancy loss, and preeclampsia—is much stronger .
# Thrombophilia Screening.
Given the relatively high incidence of thrombophilia in the population and the low incidence of VTE, universal screening during pregnancy is not costeffective.
Thus, a selective screening strategy is required.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) recommends that thrombophilia screening be considered in the following clinical circumstances: (1) a personal history of VTE with or without a recurrent risk factor such as fractures, surgery, or prolonged immobilization; and (2) a firstdegree relative (parent or sibling) with a history of a high-risk inherited thrombophilia.
As discussed previously, testing for inherited thrombophilias in women who have experienced recurrent fetal loss or adverse pregnancy outcomes is not recommended.
Methods of screening for the more common inherited thrombophilias are shown in Table 55-3.
Whenever possible, laboratory testing is performed at least 6 weeks after the thrombotic event, while the patient is not pregnant, and when she is not receiving anticoagulation or hormonal therapy.
Last, screening for hyperhomocysteinemia is not recommended .
Table 55-3.
How to Test for Thrombophilias Deep-Vein Thrombosis.
# Clinical Presentation.
During pregnancy, most venous thromboses are confined to the deep veins of the lower extremity.
Most of these are located in the iliofemoral and iliac veins without involvement of the calf veins .
In contrast, in the general population, more than 80 percent of deep-vein thromboses involve calf veins .
The vast majority are left sided .
Greer (2003) hypothesizes that this results from compression of the left iliac vein by the right iliac and ovarian arteries, both of which cross the vein only on the left side.
Yet, as described in Chapter 56 (p. 994), the ureter is compressed more on the right side.
Signs and symptoms vary depending on the degree of occlusion and the intensity of the inflammatory response.
Classically, thrombosis involving the lower extremity is abrupt in onset, and there is pain and edema of the leg and thigh.
The thrombus typically involves much of the deep-venous system to the iliofemoral region.
Occasionally, reflex arterial spasm causes a pale, cool extremity with diminished pulsations.
Calf measurements may identify a discordance in size.
Alternatively, there may be appreciable clot, yet little pain, heat, or swelling.
Importantly, calf pain, either spontaneous or in response to squeezing or to Achilles tendon stretching—Homans sign—may be caused by a strained muscle or contusion.
Importantly, 30 to 60 percent of women with a confirmed lower-extremity acute deep-vein thrombosis (DVT) have an asymptomatic pulmonary embolism (p. 986).
# Diagnosis.
Clinical diagnosis of DVT is difficult without testing and is confirmed in only 10 percent of cases .
Another challenge is that many of the common diagnostic tests that have been investigated extensively in nonpregnant patients have not been validated appropriately in pregnancy .
Shown in Figure 55-2 is one diagnostic algorithm that can be used for evaluation of pregnant women.
With a few modifications, we follow a similar evaluation at Parkland Hospital.
Figure 55-2.
Algorithm to evalate suspected venous thromboembolism in pregnancy depending upon number of YEARS criteria met.
Evidence of DVT should prompt compression ultrasound.
aThe three YEARS criteria are clinical signs of DVT, hemoptysis, and PE as the most likely diagnosis.
bThe American Thoracic Society and Society of Thoracic Radiology recommend CXR; cThe American Society of Hematology recommends pulmonary V/Q scanning.
CT = computed tomography; CTA = computed tomography angiography; CXR = chest x-ray; DVT = deep-vein thrombosis; MR = magnetic resonance; PE = pulmonary embolism; V/Q scan = ventilation perfusion scan.
From Bates, 2018; Guyatt, 2012; Leung, 2011; van der Hulle, 2019; van der Pol, 2019.
Compression
Ultrasonography With suspected DVT, the initial diagnostic test recommended is compression ultrasonography of the proximal leg veins .
The diagnosis is based on the noncompressibility and typical echoarchitecture of a thrombosed vein.
For nonpregnant patients with suspected thrombosis, the safety of withholding anticoagulation for 1 week has been established in the setting of a normal compression ultrasound examination .
Serial compression examinations are then performed because isolated undetected calf thromboses that ultimately extend into the proximal veins will do so within 1 to 2 weeks of presentation in approximately a fourth of patients.
In pregnant women, however, normal findings with ultrasonography do not always exclude a pulmonary embolism.
This is because the thrombosis may have already embolized or because it arose from iliac or other deep-pelvic veins, which are less accessible to ultrasound evaluation.
Two studies are helpful for evaluating whether serial examinations are necessary for pregnant women suspected of having a DVT.
Chan and associates (2013) studied 221 pregnant and postpartum women presenting with a suspected DVT.
The 205 women with a negative initial study result underwent serial testing, which was negative in all cases.
Of these, one woman had a pulmonary embolism 7 weeks later.
Le Gal and colleagues (2012) studied 210 pregnant and postpartum women with a suspected DVT.
Of these, 177 women without a DVT were not anticoagulated and did not undergo serial testing.
Two had an objectively confirmed thrombosis diagnosed within 3 months.
In sum, these data suggest that a negative single complete compression ultrasonography study may safely exclude the diagnosis of DVT in most pregnant women.
Magnetic Resonance Imaging This imaging technique allows excellent delineation of anatomical detail above the inguinal ligament.
Thus, in many cases, magnetic resonance (MR) imaging is immensely useful for diagnosis of iliofemoral and pelvic vein thrombosis.
The venous system can also be reconstructed using MR venography .
MR imaging is 100-percent sensitive and 90percent specific for detection of venographically proven DVT in nonpregnant patients .
Importantly, almost half of those without DVT were found to have nonthrombotic conditions that included cellulitis, myositis, edema, hematomas, and superficial phlebitis.
D-dimer Screening Tests These specific fibrin degradation products are generated when fibrinolysin (plasminogen) degrades fibrin, as occurs in thromboembolism.
Their measurement is usually incorporated into diagnostic algorithms for VTE in nonpregnant patients .
This method was shown to be accurate in the YEARS study (van der Hulle, 2017).
Screening with the D-dimer test in pregnancy, however, is problematic for several reasons.
Depending on assay sensitivity, D-dimer serum levels rise with gestational age along with substantively elevated plasma fibrinogen concentrations (Appendix, p. 1228) .
Levels are also affected by multifetal gestation and cesarean delivery (Hu, 2020; Miyamoto, 2020).
Last, D-dimer concentrations can also be elevated in pregnancy complications such as placental abruption, preeclampsia, and sepsis .
Three large prospective studies have evaluated D-dimer testing in pregnant women to diagnose VTE.
Righini and colleagues (2018) found that D-dimer measurement, bilateral leg ultrasound, and computed tomographyangiogram safely ruled out VTE.
Subsequently, van der Pol and coworkers (2019) used a pregnancy-adapted YEARS algorithm to diagnose suspected pulmonary embolism.
The algorithm used D-dimer measurements and clinical suspicion to confirm VTE.
With none of the clinical criteria present, and with the D-dimer level <1000 ng/mL, or with one or more clinical criteria present and with the D-dimer level <500 ng/mL, pulmonary embolism was safely excluded (see Fig. 55-2).
Last, the DiPEP study showed that neither clinical risk factors nor D-dimer levels were accurate in identifying pulmonary embolism in pregnant women .
They concluded that pregnant women with suspected pulmonary
embolism should all undergo imaging studies.
The findings of the YEARS study and subsequent others will no doubt guide care.
However, currently the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends against the use of D-dimer assays to diagnose VTE in pregnant women.
We agree, and in our view, these positive results need to be duplicated before adaptation of their widespread use in pregnant women.
Still, a negative D-dimer assay should be reassuring, unless VTE is the most likely diagnosis .
# Management of Venous Thromboembolism.
Optimal management of VTE during pregnancy has not undergone major clinical study to provide evidence-based practices.
There is, however, consensus for treatment with anticoagulation and limited activity.
Thrombophilia testing does not change treatment .
Anticoagulation is initiated with either unfractionated heparin (UFH) or LMWH .
Although either type is acceptable, most recommend one of the LMWHs (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020b; Kearon, 2016).
The American Society of Hematology recommends preferential use of LMWH during pregnancy because of better bioavailability, longer plasma half-life, more predictable dose response, reduced risks of osteoporosis and thrombocytopenia, and less frequent dosing .
Table 55-4.
Anticoagulation Regimen Definitions The duration of full anticoagulation varies, and no studies have defined the optimal duration for pregnancy-related thromboembolism.
In nonpregnant patients, evidence supports a minimum treatment duration of 3 months .
For pregnant patients, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends therapeutic anticoagulation for 3 to 6 months followed by intermediate or prophylactic therapy for the duration of pregnancy and the postpartum period.
If the woman is not breastfeeding, direct acting oral agents can be considered (p. 985).
Recall that pulmonary embolism develops in as many as 60 percent of patients with untreated venous thrombosis, and anticoagulation decreases this risk to less than 5 percent.
In nonpregnant patients, the mortality rate with a pulmonary embolism approximates 1 percent (Douketis, 1998; Pollack, 2011).
With DVT, over several days, leg pain dissipates.
After symptoms have abated, graded ambulation is begun.
Elastic stockings are fitted, and anticoagulation is continued.
Recovery to this stage usually takes 7 to 10 days.
Graduated compression stockings can be continued for 2 years after the diagnosis to reduce the incidence of postthrombotic syndrome .
Symptoms include chronic leg paresthesias or pain, intractable edema, skin changes, and leg ulcers.
According to the American Society of Hematology, catheter-directed thrombolytic therapy does not mitigate against this complication .
Unfractionated Heparin This agent should be considered for the initial treatment of thromboembolism and in situations in which delivery, surgery, or thrombolysis may be necessary .
UFH can be administered by one of two alternatives: (1) initial intravenous therapy followed by adjusted-dose subcutaneous UFH given every 12 hours; or (2) twice-daily, adjusted-dose subcutaneous UFH with doses adjusted to prolong the activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) into the therapeutic range 6 hours post injection .
Table 55-5.
Some Recommendations for Thromboprophylaxis During Pregnancy For intravenous therapy, several protocols are acceptable.
In general, if UFH is used, it is initiated with a bolus intravenous dose of 70 to 100 U/kg, which is 5000 to 10,000 U.
This is followed by continuous intravenous infusions beginning at 1000 U/hr or 15 to 20 U/kg/hr.
This infusion rate is titrated to achieve an aPTT 1.5 to 2.5 times control values .
Intravenous anticoagulation is maintained for about 5 to 7 days, after which treatment is converted to subcutaneous heparin to maintain the aPTT to at least 1.5 to 2.5 times control throughout the dosing interval.
For women with lupus anticoagulant, aPTT does not accurately assess heparin anticoagulation, and thus anti–factor Xa levels are preferred.
Low-molecular-weight Heparin This is a family of derivatives of unfractionated heparin, and their molecular weights average 4000 to 5000 daltons compared with 12,000 to 16,000 daltons for conventional heparin.
None of these heparins cross the placenta, and all exert their anticoagulant activity by activating antithrombin.
UFH has equivalent activity against factor Xa and thrombin compared with LMWHs, which have greater activity against factor Xa than against thrombin.
They also have a more predictable anticoagulant response and fewer bleeding complications than UFH because of their better bioavailability, longer halflife, dose-independent clearance, and decreased interference with platelets (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020b; Bates, 2018).
Their longer half-life prohibits neuraxial analgesia in laboring women.
LMWH compounds are cleared by the kidneys and must be used cautiously when there is renal dysfunction.
Several studies have shown that VTE is treated effectively with LMWH (Quinlan, 2004; Tapson, 2008).
Using serial venograms, Breddin and associates (2001) observed that these compounds were more effective than UFH in reducing thrombus size without increasing mortality rates or major bleeding complications.
Several different treatment regimens using LMWH for treatment of acute VTE are listed in Table 55-4 .
Whether LMWH requires adjustments during the course of pregnancy is controversial .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends monitoring with an anti-Xa level 4 hours after an injection with dose adjustment to maintain a therapeutic level.
Large studies using clinical end points that demonstrate an optimal therapeutic range or show that dose adjustments increase therapy, safety, or efficacy are lacking.
Accordingly, the American Society of Hematology and others have concluded that routine monitoring with anti-Xa levels is difficult to justify (Bates, 2018; McDonnell, 2017).
In general, heparin pharmacokinetics includes more rapid clearance of heparins as pregnancy progresses.
The peaks of anti-Xa activity of enoxaparin (Lovenox) across pregnancy are shown in Figure 55-3.
Similarly, tinzaparin (Innohep) with a dosage of 75 to 175 U/kg/d was necessary to achieve peak anti–factor Xa levels of 0.1 to 1.0 U/mL .
In studies of dalteparin (Fragmin) pharmacokinetics, conventional starting doses of dalteparin—100 U/kg every 12 hours—were likely insufficient to maintain full anticoagulation in pregnant women (Barbour, 2004; Jacobsen, 2003).
Thus, slightly higher doses than that shown in Table 55-4 may be required.
Figure 55-3.
Anti–factor Xa activity with repeated daily administration of 40 mg enoxaparin subcutaneously in nonpregnant women and those from each trimester .
Any concerns regarding teratogenicity of enoxaparin have been obviated (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020b; Bates, 2021).
A comprehensive study of 1267 pregnant women treated with tinzaparin found no cases of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia, maternal deaths, or complications from regional analgesia .
A total of 43 women (3.4 percent) required medical intervention for bleeding.
Of 15 stillbirths, four were judged as possibly being related to tinzaparin use.
LMWHs have been judged to be safe during breastfeeding .
Labor and Delivery Women receiving either therapeutic or prophylactic anticoagulation should be converted from LMWH to the shorter-half-life UFH in the last month of pregnancy or sooner if delivery appears imminent.
The purpose of conversion to UFH has less to do with any risk of maternal bleeding at the time of delivery, but rather with neuraxial blockade complicated by an epidural or spinal hematoma .
The Society for Obstetric Anesthesia and Perinatology recommends that UFH low-dose thromboprophylaxis be withheld for 4 to 6 hours; UFH intermediate-dose thromboprophylaxis for 12 hours; and UFH therapeutic dose for 24 hours before neuraxial analgesia .
For LMWH, the Society recommends to withhold low doses for 12 hours; intermediate doses 12 to 24 hours;
and therapeutic doses 24 hours.
If a woman begins labor while taking UFH, clearance can be verified by an aPTT.
Reversal of heparin with protamine sulfate—1 mg per 100 units heparin with a maximum dose of 50 mg—is rarely required and is not indicated with a prophylactic dose of heparin.
For women in whom anticoagulation therapy has temporarily been discontinued, pneumatic compression devices are recommended.
Warfarin Compounds Vitamin K antagonists are generally contraindicated because they readily cross the placenta and cause fetal death and malformations from hemorrhages.
This is discussed in detail in Chapter 8 (p. 156).
Their sole antepartum use is in women with a mechanical heart valve .
These compounds do not accumulate in breast milk and are thus safe during breastfeeding.
Postpartum venous thrombosis is usually treated with intravenous heparin and oral warfarin initiated simultaneously.
The initial dose of warfarin is 5 to 10 mg for the first 2 days.
Subsequent doses are titrated to achieve an international normalized ratio (INR) of 2 to 3.
To avoid paradoxical thrombosis and skin necrosis from the early antiprotein C effect of warfarin, these women are maintained on therapeutic doses of UFH or LMWH for 5 days and until the INR is in a therapeutic range for 2 consecutive days .
Treatment in the puerperium may require larger doses of anticoagulant.
Brooks and colleagues (2002) compared anticoagulation in postpartum women with that of age-matched nonpregnant controls.
The former required a significantly larger median total dose of warfarin—45 versus 24 mg—and a longer time—7 versus 4 days—to achieve the target INR.
Direct-acting Oral Anticoagulants Of these newer oral anticoagulants, dabigatran (Pradaxa) inhibits thrombin and rivaroxaban (Xarelto) and apixaban (Eliquis) inhibit factor Xa.
These agents are becoming the drugs of choice for nonpregnant subjects with thromboembolism .
Currently, very few reports address these newer agents during pregnancy and breastfeeding, and thus the human reproductive risks are essentially unknown (Lameijer, 2018; Rosenbloom, 2019).
Despite this, the GARFIELD-VTE study reported that direct-acting oral anticoagulant use in pregnant women was gaining favor .
Dabigatran crosses the placenta, however, it is unknown whether any of these agents are excreted in breast milk .
At this time, because of the potential for infant harm, a decision should be made to either avoid breastfeeding or use an alternative anticoagulant, such as warfarin, in breastfeeding women (Bates, 2021; Kruger, 2019).
# Complications of Anticoagulation.
Three significant complications associated with anticoagulation are hemorrhage, thrombocytopenia, and osteoporosis.
The latter two are unique to heparin, and their risk may be reduced with LMWHs.
The most serious complication is hemorrhage, which is more likely if there has been recent surgery or lacerations.
Troublesome bleeding is also more likely if the heparin dosage is excessive.
Unfortunately, management schemes using laboratory testing to identify when a heparin dosage is sufficient to inhibit further thrombosis, yet not cause serious hemorrhage, have been discouraging.
Heparin-induced Thrombocytopenia There are two types—the most common is a nonimmune, benign, reversible thrombocytopenia that develops within the first few days of therapy and resolves in approximately 5 days without therapy cessation.
The second is the severe form of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia, which results from an immune reaction involving IgG antibodies directed against complexes of platelet factor 4 and heparin.
The diagnosis of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) is based on a drop in the platelet count of more than 50 percent or thrombosis beginning 5 to 10 days after the start of heparin in association with the appearance of platelet-activating HIT antibodies.
The fall in platelet count in HIT occurs rapidly—over a period of 1 to 3 days— and is assessed relative to the highest platelet count after the start of heparin.
The typical nadir is 40,000 to 80,000
platelets per microliter .
Although the incidence of HIT is approximately 3 to 5 percent in nonpregnant individuals, it is <0.1 percent in obstetrical patients .
Fausett and coworkers (2001) reported no cases among 244 heparin-treated gravidas compared with 10 among 244 nonpregnant patients.
Accordingly, the American College of Chest Physicians recommends against platelet count monitoring when the risk of HIT is considered to be <1 percent .
In others, they suggest monitoring every 2 or 3 days from day 4 until 14.
Women with a presumptive diagnosis of HIT should have laboratory testing for antiplatelet antibodies or by functional assays.
However, these tests often require several days to return results, so initial management should be directed by clinical findings.
Heparin therapy is stopped, and alternative anticoagulation initiated.
LMWH may not be entirely safe because it has some cross reactivity with UFH.
The American Society of Hematology recommends use of fondaparinux (Arixtra), which is a pentasaccharide factor Xa inhibitor .
Successful use in pregnancy has been reported (De Carolis, 2015; Elsaigh, 2015).
Last, platelet transfusions are avoided .
Heparin-induced Osteoporosis Bone loss may develop with long-term heparin administration—usually 6 months or longer—and is more prevalent in cigarette smokers.
UFH can cause osteopenia, and this is less likely with LMWHs. Women treated with any heparin should be encouraged to take an oral daily 1500-mg calcium supplement (Cunningham, 2005; Lockwood, 2012).
# Anticoagulation and Abortion.
The treatment of DVT with heparin does not preclude pregnancy termination by careful curettage.
After the products are removed without trauma to the reproductive tract, full-dose heparin can be restarted in several hours.
# Anticoagulation and Delivery.
The effects of heparin on blood loss at delivery depend on several variables: (1) dose, route, and timing of administration; (2) number and depth of incisions and lacerations; (3) intensity of postpartum myometrial contractions; and (4) presence of other coagulation defects.
Blood loss should not be greatly increased with vaginal delivery if there are no lacerations, and the uterus promptly contracts.
Unfortunately, such ideal circumstances do not always prevail.
Thus, heparin therapy generally is stopped during labor and delivery.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends restarting UFH or LMWH no sooner than 4 to 6 hours after vaginal delivery or 6 to 12 hours after cesarean delivery.
From their review, Moriuchi and associates (2019) found that thromboprophylaxis started within 24 hours after cesarean delivery was safe.
At Parkland Hospital, we wait at least 24 hours to restart therapeutic-dose heparin after cesarean delivery or after vaginal delivery with significant lacerations.
Superficial Venous Thrombophlebitis.
Thrombosis limited strictly to the superficial veins of the saphenous system is typically associated with varicosities or as a sequela of an indwelling intravenous catheter.
It is treated with analgesia, elastic support, heat, and rest.
Superficial vein thrombosis raises the risk of DVT four- to six-fold.
In a metaanalysis of nonpregnant patients with thrombophlebitis, 18 percent had a concomitant DVT and 7 percent had a pulmonary embolism .
Although controversial, the American Society of Hematology suggests LMWH therapy .
Pulmonary Embolism.
Although it causes approximately 10 percent of maternal deaths, pulmonary embolism is relatively uncommon during pregnancy and the puerperium.
According to Marik and Plante (2008), 70 percent of gravidas presenting with a pulmonary embolism have associated clinical evidence of DVT.
And recall that between 30 and 60 percent of women with a DVT will have a coexisting silent pulmonary embolism.
# Clinical Presentation.
In almost 2500 nonpregnant patients with a proven pulmonary embolism, symptoms included dyspnea in 82 percent, chest pain in 49 percent, cough in 20 percent, syncope in 14 percent, and hemoptysis in 7 percent .
Other predominant
clinical findings typically include tachypnea, apprehension, and tachycardia.
In some cases, an accentuated pulmonic closure sound, rales, and/or friction rub is heard.
Right axis deviation and T-wave inversion in the anterior chest leads may be evident on the electrocardiogram.
In most cases, chest radiography results are normal.
In others, nonspecific findings may include atelectasis, an infiltrate, cardiomegaly, or an effusion.
Vascular markings in the lung region supplied by the obstructed artery can be lost.
Although most women are hypoxemic, a normal arterial blood gas analysis does not exclude pulmonary embolism.
Approximately a third of young patients have PO2 values >80 mm Hg.
Thus, the alveolar- arterial oxygen tension difference is a more useful indicator of disease.
More than 86 percent of patients with acute pulmonary embolism will have an alveolar-arterial difference >20 mm Hg .
Even with massive pulmonary embolism, signs, symptoms, and laboratory data to support the diagnosis may be deceptively nonspecific.
# Massive and Submassive Pulmonary Embolism.
Defined as embolism causing hemodynamic instability, these account for 5 to 10 percent of cases (Handal-Örefice, 2019).
Acute mechanical obstruction of the pulmonary vasculature causes increased vascular resistance and pulmonary hypertension followed by acute right ventricular dilation.
In otherwise healthy patients, significant pulmonary hypertension does not develop until 60 to 75 percent of the pulmonary vascular tree is occluded .
Moreover, circulatory collapse requires 75- to 80-percent obstruction.
This is depicted in Figure 55-4 and emphasizes that most acutely symptomatic emboli are large and likely a saddle embolism .
These are suspected when the pulmonary artery pressure is substantively increased as estimated by echocardiography.
Figure 55-4.
Schematic of pulmonary arterial circulation.
Note that the cross-sectional area of the pulmonary trunk and the combined pulmonary arteries is 9 cm.
A large saddle embolism could occlude 50 to 90 percent of the pulmonary tree, causing hemodynamic instability.
As the arteries give off distal branches, the total surface area rapidly increases, that is, 13 cm for the combined five lobar arteries, 36 cm for the combined 19 segmental arteries, and more than 800 cm for the total 65 subsegmental arterial branches.
Thus, hemodynamic instability is less likely with emboli past the lobar arteries.
Submassive embolism is diagnosed when there is evidence of right ventricular dysfunction (Handal-Örefice, 2019).
The mortality rate approaches 25 percent, which compares with a 1-percent rate without such dysfunction .
It is important in these cases to infuse crystalloids carefully and to support blood pressure with vasopressors.
Aggressive intravenous fluid infusion has been associated with worsening right-sided ventricular dysfunction .
As discussed on page 988, oxygen treatment, tracheal intubation, and mechanical ventilation are completed preparatory to thrombolysis, filter placement, or embolectomy.
# Diagnosis.
In most cases, recognition of a pulmonary embolism requires a high index of suspicion that prompts objective evaluation.
Exposure of the mother and fetus to ionizing radiation is a concern when investigating a suspected pulmonary embolism during pregnancy.
However, this concern is largely overruled by the hazards of missing a potentially fatal diagnosis.
Moreover, erroneously assigning a diagnosis of pulmonary embolism to a pregnant woman is also fraught with problems.
It unnecessarily exposes the mother and fetus to the risks of anticoagulation treatment and will impact delivery plans, future contraception, and thromboprophylaxis during subsequent pregnancies.
Therefore, investigations should aim for diagnostic certainty .
Diagnosis of a pulmonary embolism follows the same algorithm as for DVT shown in Figure 55-2.
In addition to compression ultrasound of the extremities, if a pulmonary embolism is suspected, chest x-ray and electrocardiogram may be revealing.
Echocardiography is useful to detect other
conditions that mimic pulmonary embolism—acute myocardial infarction, pericardial tamponade, and aortic dissection.
Further imaging with computed tomography (CT) scanning, MR imaging, or ventilationperfusion lung scanning confirms the diagnosis .
As discussed later (p. 988), the American Society of Hematology recommends lung scanning as the first-line diagnostic tool .
At Parkland Hospital we preferentially use CT-pulmonary angiography for suspected pulmonary embolism.
Computed Tomographic Pulmonary Angiography Multidetector CT-pulmonary angiography (CTPA) is the most commonly employed technique to diagnose pulmonary embolism in nonpregnant patients.
The technique is described further in Chapter 49 (p. 874), and an imaging example is shown in Figure 55-5.
The estimated fetal radiation exposure averages 0.45 to 0.6 mGy.
The estimated maternal breast dose is 10 to 70 mGy .
Figure 55-5.
Axial image of the chest from a four-channel multidetector spiral computed tomographic scan performed after administration of intravenous contrast.
There is enhancement of the pulmonary artery with a large thrombus on the right (arrow) consistent with pulmonary embolism.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Michael Landay.
CTPA has many advantages, but we find that the higher resolution allows detection of previously inaccessible smaller distal emboli that have uncertain clinical significance.
Similar observations have been reported by others (Anderson, 2007; Hall, 2009).
Bourjeily and colleagues (2012) performed a follow-up study of 318 pregnant women who had a negative CTPA performed for a suspected pulmonary embolism.
All were seen 3 months following their initial presentation or at 6 weeks postpartum.
None of these women were subsequently diagnosed with a thromboembolism.
Ventilation-Perfusion Scintigraphy Lung Scan This technique involves a small dose of radiotracer such as intravenously administered technetium-99m macroaggregated albumin.
There is negligible fetal and maternal breast radiation exposure—0.1 to 0.4 mGy.
The scan may not provide a definite diagnosis because many other conditions can cause perfusion defects.
Examples are pneumonia or local bronchospasm.
Chan and coworkers (2002) found that a fourth of ventilation-perfusion scans in pregnant women were nondiagnostic.
In these instances, CTPA is preferred .
To compare the performance of lung scintigraphy and CTPA, Revel and associates (2011) evaluated 137 pregnant women with suspected pulmonary embolism.
The two modalities performed comparably and had no significant differences between the proportions of positive, negative, or indeterminate results.
Specifically, the proportion of indeterminate results for both approximated 20 percent, Similarly, one systematic review concluded that both CTPA and lung scintigraphy seem appropriate for exclusion of pulmonary embolism during pregnancy (van Mens, 2017).
Intravascular Pulmonary Angiography This requires catheterization of the right side of the heart and is considered the reference test for pulmonary embolism.
With newer-generation multidetector CT scanners, however, the role of invasive pulmonary angiography has been questioned.
This is especially true given the higher radiation exposure for the fetus .
Other detractions are that it can be time consuming, uncomfortable, and associated with dyeinduced allergy and renal failure.
It is reserved for confirmation when less invasive tests are equivocal.
# Management.
Immediate treatment for pulmonary embolism is full anticoagulation similar to that for DVT as discussed on page 982 and shown in Table 55-4.
There are several complementary procedures that may be indicated.
Vena Caval Filters The woman who has very recently suffered a pulmonary embolism and who must undergo cesarean delivery presents a particularly serious problem.
Reversal of anticoagulation may be followed by another embolus, and surgery while fully anticoagulated frequently results in life-threatening hemorrhage or troublesome hematomas.
In these cases, placement of a vena caval filter should be considered
before surgery .
Moreover, in the very infrequent circumstances in which heparin therapy fails to prevent recurrent pulmonary embolism from the pelvis or legs or in which embolism develops from these sites despite heparin treatment, a vena caval filter may also be indicated.
Such filters can also be used following massive emboli in patients who are not candidates for thrombolysis.
The device is inserted through either the jugular or femoral vein and can be inserted during labor .
Routine filter placement has no added advantage to heparin given alone .
Retrievable filters may be used as short-term protection and then removed 1 to 2 weeks later .
From their systematic review, Harris and colleagues (2016) found that complication rates in pregnant women with vena caval filters are comparable to those in nonpregnant patients.
In another series of 24 filters placed in obstetrical patients, 29 percent had complications including removal failure .
Thrombolysis Compared with heparin, thrombolytic agents provide more rapid lysis of pulmonary clots and improvement of pulmonary hypertension in lifethreatening cases (Bates, 2021; Goldhaber, 2018).
In one study of nonpregnant patients receiving heparin for an acute submassive pulmonary embolism, those receiving the recombinant tissue plasminogen activator alteplase had a lower risk of death or treatment escalation .
One metaanalysis of trials involving nonpregnant patients reported that the risk of recurrence or death was significantly lower in patients given thrombolytic agents and heparin compared with those given heparin alone— 10 versus 17 percent .
Importantly, however, there were five —2 percent—fatal bleeding episodes in the thrombolysis group and none in the heparin-only group.
There have been several case reports and reviews of thrombolysis in pregnant women.
Leonhardt and coworkers (2006) identified 28 reports of tissue plasminogen activator use during pregnancy.
Ten cases were for thromboembolism.
Complication rates were similar to those in nonpregnant patients, and the authors concluded that such therapy should not be withheld during pregnancy if indicated.
Akazawa and Nishida (2017) reviewed 13 cases of systemic thrombolytic therapy administered during the first 48 hours after delivery.
Blood transfusion was required in five of the eight cesarean deliveries, including three cases of hysterectomy and two cases of hematoma drainage.
Sousa-Gomes and associates (2019) reviewed outcomes in 141 pregnant women undergoing thrombolysis for VTE or stroke.
Maternal death complicated 3 percent of cases, and major bleeding occurred in 9 percent.
Embolectomy Given the efficacy of thrombolysis and filters, surgical embolectomy is uncommonly indicated.
Published experience with emergency embolectomy during pregnancy is limited to case reports (Colombier, 2015; Saeed, 2014).
From their review, Ahearn and colleagues (2002) found that although the operative risk to the mother is reasonable, the stillbirth rate is 20 to 40 percent.
Thromboprophylaxis.
A Cochrane review of guidelines for thromboprophylaxis in pregnancy concluded that there is a lack of overall agreement about which women should be offered thromboprophylaxis .
The American Society of Hematology summarized that evidence-based recommendations rely largely on observational studies and on data extrapolated from nonpregnant patients.
In many cases, this led them to suggest—rather than recommend—various schemes for thromboprophylaxis .
In an earlier study, Cleary-Goldman and coworkers (2007) surveyed 151 fellows of the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and reported that intervention without a clear indication is common.
Table 55-5 lists several consensus recommendations for thromboprophylaxis.
In some cases, more than one option is listed, thus illustrating the confusion that currently reigns.
It is important to emphasize that the decision to treat with anticoagulation in pregnancy is influenced by personal VTE history, family history of VTE, severity of thrombophilias, and additional risk factors such
as obesity, cesarean delivery, or prolonged immobility .
# Prior Venous Thromboembolism.
In general, either antepartum surveillance or heparin prophylaxis is recommended for women with prior VTE but without a recurrent risk factor.
Tengborn and associates (1989), however, suggested that such management may not be effective.
They reported outcomes in 87 pregnant Swedish women who had prior thromboembolic disease and were not tested for thrombophilias.
Despite unfractionated heparin prophylaxis, which was usually 5000 U twice daily, 15 percent developed antepartum VTE recurrence.
This compared with 12 percent not given heparin.
Brill-Edwards and colleagues (2000) prospectively studied 125 pregnant women with a single prior VTE.
Antepartum heparin was not given, but anticoagulant therapy was given for 4 to 6 weeks postpartum.
Six women had a recurrent venous thrombosis, but there were no recurrences in women without a known thrombophilia or whose prior thrombosis was associated with a temporary risk factor.
A study of 88 women without antiphospholipid antibodies and who were not given antithrombotic prophylaxis reported a subsequent pregnancy- or puerperium-related VTE in 22 percent .
Of 20 women whose original thrombosis was associated with a transient risk factor—not including pregnancy or oral contraceptive use—there were no recurrences during pregnancy, but two during the puerperium.
These findings imply that women with a prior thrombosis in association with a thrombophilia or in the absence of a temporary risk factor generally should be given both antepartum and postpartum prophylaxis .
These data also suggest that for women with a prior VTE, antithrombotic prophylaxis during pregnancy could be tailored according to the circumstances of the original event.
It is important to emphasize that VTE may recur despite antithrombotic prophylaxis.
A study of 270 women who had at least one previous VTE found that 10 percent suffered a recurrent VTE .
Twelve of these recurrences occurred early in pregnancy before the initiation of antithrombotic prophylaxis, and 16 occurred despite prophylactic use of LMWH.
Our practice at Parkland Hospital for many years for women with a history of prior VTE was to administer subcutaneous UFH, 5000 to 7500 units two to three times daily.
More recently, we have used 40 mg of enoxaparin given subcutaneously daily with transition to UFH near delivery.
With either regimen, the recurrence of documented DVT embolization has been uncommon.
# Cesarean Delivery.
The risk for DVT and especially for fatal thromboembolism rises many fold following cesarean delivery compared with that after vaginal delivery.
When considering that a third of women giving birth in the United States yearly undergo cesarean delivery, pulmonary embolism is understandably a major cause of maternal mortality (Creanga, 2017; Petersen, 2019).
That said, the lack of consensus described earlier by Middleton and coworkers (2021) creates considerable variation in the current recommendations promulgated by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, the Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists, and the American College of Chest Physicians .
Adherence to individual society guidelines following cesarean delivery confers a greater risk in some instances.
According to the Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2020), if American College guidelines were followed, only 1 percent of these women would be candidates for thromboprophylaxis.
Almost 85 percent of the same cohort would be given thromboprophylaxis following Royal College guidelines and about 35 percent if American College of Chest Physician guidelines were followed.
Some comparisons of these thromboprophylaxis guidelines are shown in Table 55-6.
TABLE 55-6.
Thromboprophylaxis Guidelines for Women Undergoing Cesarean Delivery Since 2011, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends placement of pneumatic compression devices before cesarean delivery for all women not already receiving thromboprophylaxis.
This recommendation was
based primarily on consensus and expert opinion.
For patients undergoing cesarean delivery with additional risk factors for thromboembolism, both pneumatic compression devices and UFH or LMWH may be recommended.
The College stipulated that cesarean delivery in an emergency setting should not be delayed because of the time necessary to begin thromboprophylaxis.
Implementation of this strategy by the Hospital Corporation of America, the largest for-profit obstetrical health care delivery system in the United States, was associated with a reduction in deaths from pulmonary embolism from 7 of 458,097 cesarean births to 1 of 465,880 cesarean births (Clark, 2011, 2014).
In 2016, the National Partnership for Maternal Safety published several consensus recommendations for the prevention of maternal VTE (D’Alton, 2016).
These recommendations included expanded use of antenatal thromboprophylaxis for women hospitalized 3 days or longer, expanded use of prophylaxis during and after vaginal delivery, and expanded use of pharmacological prophylaxis to most women after cesarean delivery.
In response, Sibai and Rouse (2016) expressed concern that these new recommendations derive from sparse data of questionable applicability to obstetrical patients.
They called for better quality evidence to measure the benefits, harms, and costs of increased pharmacological thromboprophylaxis.
As aptly expressed by Macones (2017), “an intervention, such as increased postcesarean pharmacologic thromboprophylaxis, where there are legitimate concerns about efficacy and safety, requires a much higher degree of evidence before a national guideline is implemented.
We agree with these sentiments.